Johnny Otis and Bill Griffiths Video Collection, circa 1975-1977 SC 100
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Johnny Otis and Bill Griffiths Video Collection
circa 1975-1977
Archives of African American Music and Culture
Otis, Johnny, 1921-2012
Griffiths, Bill, 1924-2015
SC 100
6 Videotape Reels 2 in.
10 Videocassettes U-matic
14 Videocassettes BetacamSP
6 Videocassettes VHS
7 Videocassettes DigiBeta
5 Videocassettes IMX MPEG-2
Original video masters for thirteen Johnny Otis Show television programs, taped in a Los Angeles studio by Griffiths circa 1975 and featuring such guest artists as Delmar "Mighty Mouth" Evans, Marie Adams & the Three Tons of Joy, Joe Turner, Shuggie Otis, Pee Wee Crayton, and Eddie "Cleanhead" Vinson. Also included are five hours of unedited footage from Johnny Otis's Oldies But Goodies musical revue, a live show in L.A. that featured popular artists of the rock & roll era lip-synching to their hit recordings. Taped by Griffith from 1975-1977, over 100 songs are performed by artists such as Emma James, Richard Berry, the Penguins, the Coasters, Shirley & Lee, Ted Taylor, Bobby Day, and the Medallions.
Arrangement
Arranged in 2 series:
Series 1: The Johnny Otis Show
Series 2: Johnny Otis's Oldies But Goodies
--- Subseries 2.1: Artist performances
--- Subseries 2.2: Crowd dancers clips
Biographical / Historical
In the 1970s an interesting collaboration began in Los Angeles between two entertainment industry pioneers: Johnny Otis, the legendary R&B songwriter and bandleader, and Bill Griffiths, one of the original promoters of roller derby and former owner of the L.A. Thunderbirds franchise. Otis's success as a recording artist and radio deejay led to an opportunity to host a weekly television variety show for KTTV in L.A., which aired for eight years beginning in the mid-1950s as The Johnny Otis Show. Griffiths, who at that time ran an ad agency, assisted by finding sponsors for the show and a friendship formed between the two men. By the 1970s Griffiths had his own TV truck, primarily used for filming roller derby events, and offered to shoot some of Otis's live shows. The resulting video footage was recently donated to the AAAMC by Otis and Griffiths and consists of two distinct series.
Access Restrictions
Use of time-based media materials (audio and video) may require production of listening or viewing copies.
Access to streaming audio, moving image, and full resolution digital image materials may currently be restricted to researchers who can authenticate with an IU account or who are physically present on campus. Remote streaming to individual researchers may be allowed with the completion of applicable forms.
For further information about access to online audiovisual materials, contact AAAMC staff at aaamc@indiana.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the AAAMC by Johnny Otis and Bill Griffiths in 2004.
Related Materials
Additional materials related to Johnny Otis can be found in the Johnny Otis Collection (SC 106) at the AAAMC.
Scope and Contents
The Johnny Otis Show collection is comprised of original video masters for 13 half-hour television programs taped in a Los Angeles studio circa 1975. Billed as "America's only rhythm and blues TV series," the program featured Johnny Otis with his stellar band and back-up singers, the Otisettes, along with many of the great R&B artists as guests. Regulars included Delmar "Mighty Mouth" Evans, Marie Adams & the Three Tons of Joy, Joe Turner, Twiggy Hamilton, Roy Milton, Shuggie Otis (Johnny's son), Pee Wee Crayton, Eddie "Cleanhead" Vinson, and Cardella Di Millo. Melody Maker (a London magazine) described the program as "a happy, unpretentious show that harks back to the halcyon days of R&B" while a San Francisco Chronicle critic exclaimed, "if you would like an instant history of one large segment of popular music, The Johnny Otis Show must be one of the greatest blues/R&B/rock & roll shows ever put together as one act!"
The Johnny Otis's Oldies but Goodies musical revue was a live show in L.A., similar in nature to the popular television programs American Bandstand and Soul Train, where popular artists lip-synched to their hit recordings while members of the audience danced along. Otis's revue featured R&B artists that had been popular during the early days of the rock & roll era, hence the "oldies" designation. Griffiths taped many of these performances between 1975 and 1977, resulting in approximately five hours of footage and including nearly 100 hit songs. Between segments Otis casually chatted with guests before introducing their songs. Of particular interest are numerous performances by Etta James, who was originally discovered by Otis, and who teams up with Richard Berry on her hit song "Roll With Me Henry." Other performers include the Penguins, the Coasters, Richard Berry, Ted Taylor, Richard Berry, Shirley & Lee, Bobby Day, the Medallions, Joe Houston, the Robins, Gene & Eunice, and many more.
These videos are highly recommended for anyone interested in the history and development of black music and the classic sound of R&B.
- 1. The Johnny Otis Show
  - Program 1, 1975-12-15
    Shelf numbers
    VCU 50; VCBSP 1
    Scope and Contents
    Otisettes -- Get Ready
    Delmar Evans -- In the Evening
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Little Bitty Pretty One
    Johnny Otis -- Hand Jive
    Eddie "Cleanhead" Vinson -- Cleanhead's Blues
    Otisettes -- Dance to the Music
    Eddie "Cleanhead" Vinson -- Kidney Stew
    Cast -- Boogie Woogie Bye Bye
    Online Access
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/k71n49vb60
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/r66j03f88f
    General
    Personnel: J. Otis, piano; Blue Mitchell, trumpet; Gene Connors, trombone; Red Holloway, sax; Jim Wynn, sax; Robert Dingle, drums; Jimmy Smith, Jr. – bass; Art Hillary – organ; James Bradshaw – guitar; Jessie Johnson - guitar
  - Program 2, 1975-12-17
    VCU 51; VCBSP 2
    Otisettes -- Shake
    Eddie "Cleanhead" Vinson -- Hold It Right There
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Mo Jo
    Delmar Evans -- Further On Up the Road
    Otisettes -- Will You Still Love Me Tomorrow
    Eddie "Cleanhead" Vinson -- I Took the Back Door Out
    Twiggy Hamilton -- Groovin'
    Johnny Otis Show Band -- Flyin' Home
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/v53j92hj11
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/c18d47433s
  - Program 3, 1975-12-17
    Otisettes -- Stand
    Myles & the Drifters -- My Girl
    Twiggy & the Otisettes -- Daddy's Home
    Delmar Evans -- Mustang Sally
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Mama (He Treats Your Daughter Mean)
    Myles & the Drifters -- This Magic Moment
    Johnny Otis, Twiggy, Delmar Evans -- Let the Good Times Roll
    Cast -- Honky Tonk
  - Program 4, 1975-12-15
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Dust My Broom
    Joe Turner -- Shake Rattle and Roll
    Delmar Evans -- Funky Broadway
    Otisettes -- Mockingbird/Mr. Lee
    Johnny Otis & Delmar Evans -- Don't Start Me Talking
    Joe Turner -- Chains of Love
  - Program 5, 1975-12-18
    VCBSP 3
    Johnny Otis & Delmar Evans -- Watts Breakaway
    Joe Turner -- Honey Hush
    Otisettes -- Higher
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Ride Jockey Ride
    Twiggy Hamilton -- Feelin' All Right
    Johnny Otis & Delmar Evans -- Goin' Back to L.A.
    Joe Turner -- Nothin' to Nothin' Blues
    Johnny Otis Show Band -- Ridin' With Red
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/118r36w39m
  - Program 6, 1975-12-20
    VCU 52; VCBSP 4
    Otisettes -- You're All I Need
    Otisettes -- Sweet Soul Music
    Johnny Otis & Delmar Evans -- Country Girl
    Roy Milton -- Hush
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Money
    Johnny Otis & "Stuff" Nailon -- Castin' My Spell
    Johnny Otis Show Band -- Flea's Shuffle
    Twiggy & the Otisettes -- Dedicated to the One I Love
    Roy Milton -- Milton's Boogie
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/465544cs5t
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/k81j52xd4s
  - Program 7, 1975-12-20
    VCBSP 4; VCBSP 8
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Jim Dandy
    Delmar Evans -- Delmar's Blues
    Shuggie Otis -- Ice Cold Daydream
    Romy Rand -- It's Almost Like Being In Love
    Johnny Otis -- Baby I Got News For You
    Otisettes -- Heat Wave
    Romy Rand -- Feelings
    Shuggie Otis -- Shuggie's Boogie
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/c48356b92h
  - Program 8, 1975-12-18
    VCBSP 3; VCBSP 7
    Otisettes -- Proud Mary
    Lorez Alexandria -- You Light Up My Life
    Delmar Evans -- Tossin' & Turnin'
    Johnny Otis -- Feel So Bad
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Shake A Hand
    Twiggy & the Otisettes -- Save the Last Dance For Me
    Lorez Alexandria -- A Song For You
    Cast -- Mama Don't Allow No Boogie Woogie
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/t74c67xw8w
  - Program 9, 1975-12-18
    VCBSP 5
    Delmar Evans -- High Heel Sneakers
    "Stuff" & the Otisettes -- My Guy
    Cardella Di Milo -- Everyday I Have the Blues
    Johnny Otis -- Please Don't Leave Me
    Otisettes -- Everything You Said Came True
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Jimmy Reed Medley
    Delmar Evans -- You Better Look Out
    Cast -- Hony Tonk Train
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/k71n49vb79
  - Program 10, 1975-12-19
    VCU 55; VCBSP 6
    Otisettes -- Don't Ever Leave Me
    Delmar Evans -- Knock On Wood
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Goin' to Kansas City
    Pee Wee Crayton -- Lucille
    Barbara Figueroa -- Lover Man
    Johnny Otis -- Linda Lu
    Pee Wee Crayton -- The Things I Used to Do
    Pee Wee Crayton -- Pee Wee's Boogie
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/j33306v757
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/b19f16d90x
  - Program 11, 1975-12-19
    VCU 54; VCBSP 6; VCBSP 8
    Otisettes -- But I Ain't No More
    Johnny Otis Delmar Evans J. Johnson -- Tick Tock
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Get On Up
    Roy Milton -- Information Blues
    Gene "Mighty Flea" Connors -- The Preacher's Blues
    Twiggy & the Otisettes -- Respect
    Roy Milton -- R.M. Blues
    Cast -- Flea Wants to Blow Now
    https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/494v53m52f
  - Program 12, 1975-12-18
    VCBSP 4; VCBSP 5; VCBSP 7
    Delmar Evans -- Turn On Your Love Light
    Otisettes -- Love Makes Me Do Foolish Things
    Cardella Di Milo -- Stormy Monday
    Cardella Di Milo -- Goin' Down Slow
    Johnny Otis -- Stack-A-Lee
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Hound Dog
  - Program 13, 1975-12-19-1975-12-20
    VCU 55; VCBSP 7
    Otisettes -- Twist & Shout
    Delmar Evans -- I Pity the Fool
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- Whispers
    Twiggy Hamilton -- Fever
    Shuggie Otis -- Inspiration Information
    Marie Adams & 3 Tons of Joy -- In the Dark
    Cardella Di Milo -- 24 Hours a Day
    Johnny Otis -- Little Girl With the Hot Pants On
- 2. Johnny Otis's Oldies But Goodies
  - 2.1. Artist performances
    - Bob. B. Soxx (with substitutes) -- Why Do Lovers Break Each Others Hearts [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
      VCU 59; VCBSP 14
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/633d96m427
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/g25742bm1w
    - Bob. B. Soxx (with substitutes) -- Why Do Lovers Break Each Others Hearts [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
      VCBSP 14
    - Bob. B. Soxx (with substitutes) -- Why Do Lovers Break Each Others Hearts [Take 3], circa 1975-1977
    - Bob. B. Soxx (with substitutes) -- Why Do Lovers Break Each Others Hearts [Take 4], circa 1975-1977
      VCU 59; VCBSP 10; VCBSP 14
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/633d96m41x
    - Bob. B. Soxx (with substitutes) -- Zip A Dee Doo Da [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
      Listed as Bob. B. Soxx & The Blue Jeans on cue sheets.
    - Bob. B. Soxx (with substitutes) -- Zip A Dee Doo Da [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Bobby Day -- Little Bitty Pretty One, circa 1975-1977
      VCBSP 11
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/h63s85bp87
    - Bobby Day -- Mr. & Mrs. Rock & Roll, circa 1975-1977
    - Bobby Day -- Over and Over, circa 1975-1977
    - Bobby Day -- Rockin' Robin, circa 1975-1977
      VCU 58; VCBSP 10; VCBSP 13
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/m40x71bs7z
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/979v04403w
    - Bobby"Boris" Pickett -- Monster Mash, circa 1975-1977
      VCU 58; VCBSP 13
    - C.J. Charleton -- C.C. Rider, circa 1975-1977
      VC 1215
    - C.J. Charleton -- It's Only Make Believe, circa 1975-1977
    - Coasters (Bobby Nunn) -- Along Came Jones, circa 1975-1977
      VCU 58; VCBSP 12
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/108v33t213
    - Coasters (Bobby Nunn) -- Charlie Brown, circa 1975-1977
    - Coasters (Bobby Nunn) -- Little Egypt, circa 1975-1977
    - Coasters (Bobby Nunn) -- Poison Ivy, circa 1975-1977
      VCBSP 10
    - Coasters (Bobby Nunn) -- Searching, circa 1975-1977
    - Coasters (Bobby Nunn) -- Yakety Yak, circa 1975-1977
      VCBSP 12
    - Don Julian & The Meadowlarks -- Heaven and Paradise, circa 1975-1977
      VC 1217
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/n69m11fg6q
    - Don Julian & The Meadowlarks -- I Want You Back, circa 1975-1977
    - Don Julian & The Meadowlarks -- The Jerk, circa 1975-1977
    - Don Julian & the Meadowlarks -- The Way You Look Tonight, circa 1975-1977
      Listed on cue sheet as The Jaguars.
    - Donnie Brooks -- Comedy routine, circa 1975-1977
      VCU 57
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/742930d31h
    - Donnie Brooks -- Doll House [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Donnie Brooks -- Doll House [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
      VCU 56; VCU 57; VCBSP 9
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/465544cs4h
      https://purl.dlib.indiana.edu/iudl/media/n20395xg7b
    - Donnie Brooks -- Mission Bell, circa 1975-1977
    - Donnie Brooks -- Oldies but Goodies Medley (comedy routine) [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Donnie Brooks -- Oldies but Goodies Medley (comedy routine) [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - "Drifters" -- On Broadway, circa 1975-1977
      Roosevelt Miles group, "recreation" of Drifters = also called "West Coast Drifters" on original cue sheets.
    - "Drifters" -- Save the Last Dance For Me, circa 1975-1977
    - "Drifters" -- There Goes My Baby, circa 1975-1977
    - "Drifters" -- This Magic Moment, circa 1975-1977
    - "Drifters" -- Up On the Roof, circa 1975-1977
    - "Drifters" -- Under the Boardwalk, circa 1975-1977
    - Etta James -- At Last, circa 1975-1977
      VCU 56; VCBSP 9
    - Etta James -- Something's Got a Hold on Me, circa 1975-1977
    - Etta James -- Sunday Kind of Love, circa 1975-1977
    - Etta James -- Tell Mama, circa 1975-1977
      Shelf Number
      VCBSP 10; VC 1217
    - Etta James -- Trust In Me, circa 1975-1977
    - Etta James & Richard Berry -- Roll With Me Henry, circa 1975-1977
    - Gene & Eunice -- Ko Ko Mo, circa 1975-1977
      VCU 58; VCU 59; VCBSP 12; VCBSP 14
    - Gene & Eunice -- Poco Loco [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Gene & Eunice -- Poco Loco [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Gene & Eunice -- This Is My Story [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Gene & Eunice -- This Is My Story [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Jan & Dean (backed by Papa Du Run Run) -- Dead Man's Curve, circa 1975-1977
      VC 1218
    - Jan & Dean (backed by Papa Du Run Run) -- Ha La Lou Lou, circa 1975-1977
    - Jan & Dean (backed by Papa Du Run Run) -- Little Old Lady from Pasadena, circa 1975-1977
    - Jan & Dean (backed by Papa Du Run Run) -- Sidewalk Surfin', circa 1975-1977
    - Jan & Dean (backed by Papa Du Run Run) -- Surf City, circa 1975-1977
    - Joe Houston -- All Night Long, circa 1975-1977
    - Joe Houston -- Rockin' At the Drive-In, circa 1975-1977
    - Joe Houston -- We're Gonna Rock & Roll, circa 1975-1977
    - Little Caesar & the Romans -- Disco Hully Gully, circa 1975-1977
    - Little Caesar & the Romans -- Memories of Those Oldies But Goodies [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Little Caesar & the Romans -- Memories of Those Oldies But Goodies [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Little Caesar & the Romans -- Those Oldies But Goodies (Remind Me of You), circa 1975-1977
    - Medallions -- Buick 59, circa 1975-1977
    - Medallions -- Magic Mountain, circa 1975-1977
    - Medallions -- The Letter, circa 1975-1977
    - Nino Tempo & April Stevens -- All Strung Out Over You, circa 1975-1977
    - Nino Tempo & April Stevens -- Deep Purple, circa 1975-1977
    - Nino Tempo & April Stevens -- Put It Where You Want It, circa 1975-1977
    - Nino Tempo & April Stevens -- Sweet and Lovely, circa 1975-1977
    - Nino Tempo & April Stevens -- Whispering, circa 1975-1977
    - Papa Du Run Run -- Be True to Your School, circa 1975-1977
    - Penguins -- Earth Angel [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Penguins -- Earth Angel [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Penguins -- Hey Señorita [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Penguins -- Hey Señorita [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Penguins -- Memories of El Monte [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Penguins -- Memories of El Monte [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Penguins -- Memories of El Monte [Take 3], circa 1975-1977
    - Penguins -- Memories of El Monte [Take 4], circa 1975-1977
    - Ray Stevens -- Ahab the Arab, circa 1975-1977
    - Richard Berry -- Doin' It, circa 1975-1977
    - Richard Berry -- Have Love Will Travel, circa 1975-1977
    - Richard Berry -- Louie Louie, circa 1975-1977
    - Richard Berry - Trackin' Machine, circa 1975-1977
    - Richard Berry -- Walk Right In, circa 1975-1977
    - Richard Berry - Yama Yama Pretty Mamma, circa 1975-1977
    - Rivingtons -- Bird Is the Word, circa 1975-1977
    - Rivingtons -- Papa Ooh Mow Mow, circa 1975-1977
    - Rivingtons -- Roll On, circa 1975-1977
    - Robins -- Down In Mexico, circa 1975-1977
    - Robins -- Loop de Loop Mambo, circa 1975-1977
    - Robins -- Riot In Cell Block #9, circa 1975-1977
      VCU 58; VCBSP 11; VCBSP 13
    - Robins -- Smokey Joe's Café, circa 1975-1977
    - Rockabilly Ray Campi -- Eager Beaver Boy, circa 1975-1977
    - Rockabilly Ray Campi -- It Ain't Me [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Rockabilly Ray Campi -- It Ain't Me [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Rockabilly Ray Campi -- It Ain't Me [Take 3], circa 1975-1977
    - Rockabilly Ray Campi -- Rockit [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Rockabilly Ray Campi -- Rockit [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Rockabilly Ray Campi -- Rockit [Take 3], circa 1975-1977
    - Rollin' Collin Winsky -- Dig Those Squeaky Shoes, circa 1975-1977
    - Rollin' Collin Winsky -- Red Hot Mama, circa 1975-1977
    - Ron Holden -- Can You Talk, circa 1975-1977
    - Ron Holden -- Love You So, circa 1975-1977
    - Shirley & Lee -- Feel So Good, circa 1975-1977
    - Shirley & Lee -- I Feel Good, circa 1975-1977
    - Shirley & Lee -- I'm Gone, circa 1975-1977
    - Shirley & Lee -- Let the Good Times Roll, circa 1975-1977
    - Ted Taylor -- Be Ever Wonderful [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Ted Taylor -- Be Ever Wonderful [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Ted Taylor -- Be Ever Wonderful [Take 3], circa 1975-1977
    - Ted Taylor -- Ghetto Disco, circa 1975-1977
    - Ted Taylor -- Steal Away [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Ted Taylor -- Steal Away [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Vince Howard & the Planets -- Funk On Down [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Vince Howard & the Planets -- Funk On Down [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
    - Vince Howard & the Planets -- Funk On Down [Take 3], circa 1975-1977
    - Vince Howard & the Planets -- Promise, circa 1975-1977
    - Vince Howard & the Planets -- Stand There Mountain, circa 1975-1977
    - Young Jessie -- Do You Love Me, circa 1975-1977
    - Young Jessie -- Mary Lou [Take 1], circa 1975-1977
    - Young Jessie -- Mary Lou [Take 2], circa 1975-1977
  - 2.2. Crowd dancers clips
    - Dancing to Little Richard -- Slippin' Slidin', circa 1975-1977
    - Dancing to Fontalla Bass -- Rescue Me, circa 1975-1977
    - Dancing to Chuck Berry -- Maybelline, circa 1975-1977
    - Dancing to Rosie & the Originals -- Angel Baby, circa 1975-1977
    - Dancing to the Crystals -- He's a Rebel, circa 1975-1977
    - Dancing to the Diamonds -- Little Darling, circa 1975-1977
    - Dancing to the Righteous Brothers -- You've Lost That Loving Feeling, circa 1975-1977
    - Dancing to Fats Domino -- My Blue Heaven, circa 1975-1977
    - Dancing to Bobby Pickett -- Monster Mash, circa 1975-1977
    - Dancing to Frankie Avalon -- Venus, circa 1975-1977
    - Dancing to Gary US Bonds -- Quarter to Three, circa 1975-1977